Preliminary Inventory to the Ethel John Lindgren-Utsi Papers, 1924-1944
Hoover Institution Archives
Ethel John Lindgren-Utsi Papers,
1924-1944
79007
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize folder, 1 motion picture film reel. (1.8 linear feet)
Journals, relating to anthropological field trips to Manchuria, 1929- 1932; notes, relating to the literature of anthropology; and a film of domesticated reindeer in Manchuria.
Lindgren-Utsi, Ethel John, 1905-1988
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Biographical/Historical note
British anthropologist.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1979.
Scope and Contents note
Journals, relating to anthropological field trips to Manchuria, 1929-1932; notes, relating to the literature of anthropology; and a film of domesticated reindeer in Manchuria.
Anthropology.; China.; Ethnology--Manchuria.; Manchuria.; Moving-pictures.; Reindeer.
- ANTHROPOLOGY. (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Notes on methodology, lectures, conferences and minutes of a symposium on "Patterns of Culture", 1936.
- BARGA.
  Notes on the province of Barga and some of its ethnic groups, including a letter from V.V. Radin, dated Dec.15, 1933, describing Hailar, the capital.
- BOOKS.
  Notes, translations, excerpts from various books, studies, encyclopedias, etc., in particular notes from "The Natives of the Amur Country", by L. Schrenck. Also included is a letter from Miss Esther Vernon Jones to Prof. Lowie, concerning the carbon copies of the translations that EJL sent to him.
- BURYATS.
  Notes.
- CHINA.
  Notes on Chinese customs, terms of relationship, architecture, theatre, including notes given by Chin and some comments by Ferdinand Lessing.
- COLLECTIONS.
  Copy of the museum register of the collection deposited at the University Museum of Archeology and Ethnology, Cambridge, 1930; list of articles collected by EJL in NW Manchuria, 1931 and 1932; inventory of Numinchen, Solon and Dagur collections, Aug-Sept. 1931.
- DAGURS.
  Notes on Dagurs of Barga, June 1931; Dagur terms of relationship, burial customs, folklore and language, soldiers and `white bandits', villages and temples.
- DIARY.
  "An old note-book" and EJL's diary, copied from entries in Featherweight diary, Jan. 1934.
- FIELD-TRIPS.
  Field note-books from five expeditions in NW Manchuria.
  - 1) Ust-Urov Trip, June-Sept. 1929
    Including a supplement from O. Mamen's notes; "Kumarchen-Russian Notes" and "Romance of the Border".
  - 2) Chol Trip, Aug.-Sept. 1931
    Including two supplements and O. Mamen's account.
  - 3) Winter Trip, Oct.-Dec. 1931 (Box 2)
    Including a supplement and an extract from a letter to Valeska Bary, dated Feb.20, 1932, concerning the Reindeer Tungus visited during the Winter Trip.
  - 4) Imin Trip, March 1932
    Including a supplement.
  - 5) Larch River Trip, May-July 1932 (Box 3)
    Including a supplement and an extract from a letter from Dmitri Lavrentivich Molokov, dated June 19, 1935, filed as supplement to Larch River Trip.
- FOREIGN AFFAIRS.
  Two issues of "Memorandum of Information on Foreign Affairs", May and June 1940.
- GANJUR FAIR.
  Notes, Sept. 1931.
- GLOSSARY.
  Glossary of various items, 1932-1933.
- HAILAR OBO.
  Notes on Obo Festival (Natum), June 1929; the road Hailar-Solon Obo, June 1931; Bayin Khan Obo founded, June 1931; Solon Obo, June 1931; Yamen's visit to Hailar Obo, July 1931; Panchen Lama's visit to Hailar Obo, Sept. 1931.
- HEDIN, SVEN.
  Newspaper article on Sven Hedin's life and political standpoint, March 30, 1940.
- IRELAND.
  Notes recorded at Athlone, April 24, 1935.
- JAPAN.
  Newspaper clippings on North Japan Alps, 1939, and a transcription of a conversation with Mr. Ishikawa on current events in Japan and about Dr. Nitobe, Jan.21, 1934.
- KALLEN, H. K.
  Reprints of four of his articles:
  - "Beauty and Use: A pragmatic interpretation", May 1939
  - "Education of Jews in our time", May 1939
  - "The Meanings of `unity' among the Sciences", Sept. 1939
  - "Of War and Peace", Sept. 1939
- KHINGAN OROCHENS.
- MAMEN, O.
  Two diaries from 1929 and 1932, and a record of C.E.R. meteorological observations for Barga, 1917 to 1921.
- MISCELLANEOUS.
  List of people that EJL sent her article in G.J, June 1930; stories told by a young English university graduate girl: "An English village `John' " and "An Impression of Radcliffe hall", recorded Dec.25, 1930, and a list of scientific instruments, bought in 1931.
- MONGOLIA. (Box 4)
  "Etcetera & Mongolica", written in Peking, Jan.5, 1931 (original conversations: June 1927 - June 1928); guide to a study by Mrs. Kimiko Torii, entitled "Mongolia studied from ethnographical viewpoint" and a translation of a study by K.F. Golstunski on Mongol-Oirat Laws.
- NUMINCHEN.
  Notes on Numinchen census, terms of relationship, vocabulary, etc., including field-notes from the Winter Trip, March 1931, during which EJL spent five days among the Numinchen.
- PASSPORT ENTRIES OF E.J. LINDGREN.
  Including EJL's letter to Valeska Bary, dated Oct. 8, 1941, concerning in part her passports.
- PLAETSCHKE, BRUNO.
  Account of Dr. Bruno Plaetschke's journey to Ganchen and onwards, July 1932.
- POETRY.
  "Virginalia" - poems by Nadine Huang (Juan)? Holograph.
- PSYCHOLOGY.
  Notes on books, conferences, lectures, etc.
- REFUGEES.
  Reports concerning resettlement of refugees, 1939; newspaper clippings and extracts of correspondence relating to the fund-raising activities of the International Refugee Colonisation Society, Nov. and Dec. 1939.
- REINDEER TUNGUS.
  Field-notes on Reindeer Tungus customs, relationship terms, vocabulary, etc.; listings of Mongol and Tungus objects in the University Museum of Archeology and Ethnology, Cambridge; description of Tungus material in the Ethnographical Museum of Vladivostok and Copenhagen; list of titles of scenes from the Anthropological Film of the Reindeer Tungus of Manchuria; Granfelt's notes; Petri's description of his photographs on Siberian Tungus; notes and translations of studies on various Tungus people and languages.
- SHAMANISM.
  Notes, in particular a description of Khoan and Ba Shamans' performance, July 5-7, 1931; letter from John MacCurdy, dated April 7, 1930, on the theme of shamanism and a list of papers by EJL published before Jan.31, 1940, in which some mention is made of shamanism; speech, 1944.
- SHIROKOGOROVA - NW MANCHURIA.
  Record of a trip in that area in 1915.
- SIMPSON, MAY.
  Her recollections of Ethel May Roe.
- SINKIANG.
  Description of the tribes of Sinkiang, Oct. 1929, and the account of EJL's encounter with the Yakut Simen Starostin, Aug. 1934.
- SOLONS.
  Notes on Solon vocabulary and drumsticks, including notes taken during the Winter Trip.
- THREE RIVERS HISTORY.
  Extract of a letter from Bishop Jonah of Manchuli describing the Three Rivers region.
- TORGUT FROM ASTRAKHAN.
  Historical, biographical and anthropological notes, 1931.
- URGA.
  Notes recorded in 1928.
- ZIONISM.
  "The Jewish Organizations' ABC", 1939; report concerning possibilities for Jewish settlement in Surinam (Netherlands Guiana), 1939, and a reprint of a conference by J. and J. Tharaud, 1926, on the subject of Israel.
- Motion Picture Film (Film Shelf)
  - 16mm film of domesticated reindeer in Manchuria